Guide to the Halbreich Papers 1941-1946 (bulk 1944-1945) MS 2959
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Series I: Letters from Lester to Shirley, 1943 - 1945
  He explains that a new ALNAV has clarified the situation regarding the number of points needed for discharge and states how he will have 44.5 points in December, enough to be decommissioned. He explains how they are at San Pedro on the island of Samar to bring between 16 and 17 hundred enlisted men back to the states. He tells how they are on the way back to San Francisco and reveals that he feels sad because he worries that his son’s image of ‘daddy’ will be of Shirley’s father and not him. He puts plans in motion to meet Shirley first in a hotel and spend a few days with just her alone, then to return to Brooklyn and meet his son, Jeff, just the three of them, and then see the rest of their family.
  - Letters, October 1943, 1943 October 6-15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, October 1943, 1943 October 16-26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, July 1944, 1944 July 16-22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, July 1944, 1944 July 22-31 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Writes after learning about the birth of their son and describes how he received the news.
  - Letters, August 1944, 1944 August 2-17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters, August 1944, 1944 August 18-31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, September 1944, 1944 September 1-17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters, September 1944, 1944 September 18-29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, October 1944, 1944 October 1-9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters, October 1944, 1944 October 11-21 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letters, October 1944, 1944 October 24-31 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters, November 1944, 1944 November 1-16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes a letter describing a ceremony that took place on the ship when they were passing the equator, whereby people who had not crossed the line before were referred to as 'shellbacks' and became 'pollywogs' once they had passed the equator.
  - Letters, November 1944, 1944 November 16-30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters, December 1944, 1944 December 3-18 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, December 1944, 1944 December 19-31 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, January 1945, 1945 January 2-12 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, January 1945, 1945 January 14-24 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, January 1945, 1945 January 25-31 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, February 1945, 1945 February 2-15 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, February 1945, 1945 February 16-28 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Letters, March 1945, 1945 March 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Letters, March 1945, 1945 March 11-19 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Letters, March 1945, 1945 March 19-30 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Letters, April 1945, 1945 April 1-17 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Letters, April 1945, 1945 April 18-30 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Letters, May 1945, 1945 May 1-12 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes a letter dated April 5th – May 2nd detailing Lester's experience of the invasion of Okinawa.
  - Letters, May 1945, 1945 May 14-31 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Letters, June 1945, 1945 June 2-11 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Letters, June 1945, 1945 June 13-21 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters, June 1945, 1945 June 22-30 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, July 1945, 1945 July 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters, July 1945, 1945 July 10-31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters, August 1945, 1945 August 20-30 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Letters, September 1945, 1945 September 3-14 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters, September 1945, 1945 September 15-30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Letters, October 1945, 1945 October 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters, October 1945, 1945 October 16-26 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Lester provides a humorous account of going to an officer's club during liberty time and an interaction he had with a Japanese female worker at the club (letter dated October 16th).
  - Letters, November 1945, 1945 November 4-8 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series II: Letters from Shirley to Lester, 1943 - 1945
  The majority of Shirley’s letters reflect on their relationship and her love for Lester and their new born baby, Jeffrey Neal. She talks about her friend’s husbands who are also away at war and wonders whether they are being faithful to their wives. Shirley tells how many women are seeing other men while their husbands are away. Both Shirley and Lester repeatedly reassure one another of their fidelity.
  Much of the correspondence concern plans for their future; where they will live after the war is over, whether they will rent or buy a premises and where Lester will set up a practice. Shirley describes the level of inflation that has taken place since the beginning of the war and how there is a serious housing crisis in New York due to the influx of men returning. She talks about the elections for mayor in NYC between Morris, Goldstein and O’Dwyer and remarks on what she feels is a comedic element of the elections as, she claims, the ‘Jews are voting for O’Dwyer and the Catholics for Goldstein’. She writes a poem in which she mentions Tammany Hall.
  A recurring theme throughout Shirley’s letters is motherhood. Throughout all of Shirley’s letters she provides detailed descriptions of their son, Jeffrey, as he goes through the various stages of infancy. Her accounts of daily life with Jeff provide an interesting insight into motherhood in the 1940s, for example how rationing affected items such as children’s shoes. In a letter dated March 24, 1945, when complaining of how Jeff cries when in the stroller and is not pushed, she gives an example of ‘leaving him outside a store’ while she went inside to buy groceries and tells how other women kept coming in to tell her that her baby was crying. This was apparently a very common practice during this period.
  Shirley’s letters give the reader a good sense of what it was like for the average female in the US while their husband/boyfriend was away at war. During the war Shirley lived with her parents. She gives an insight into her family life, telling how she attended Broadway shows, plays at Madison Square Garden, and dined with them at upscale restaurants, such as Arnold Rothstein's ‘Longchamps.' She also mentions having maids, one in particular, Nora, who she described as ‘their colored girl’. Shirley talks extensively about her female friends and describes how they regularly called to each other’s houses and socialized with each other. She gives accounts of many of the conversations had at these social gatherings, providing an interesting insight into what other women were experiencing during this time. She speaks of many of her friend’s relationships and how they were managing life without their husbands/partners/family members who are away at war. She remarks on how her sister Elaine reacted to her 21 year-old boyfriend returning from the war and describes how her sister was a little disappointed in him as she had built him up in her head to be more mature. She was surprised to find he was just as immature as he was when he left, a poignant reminder of the youth of some of the men who were at war and the many who did not return. In another letter, written in April 1945, Shirley informs Lester that a friend of theirs was killed in Leyte, Philippines. This man was due to wed Shirley’s close friend Gloria, who is frequently mentioned throughout the letters. Shirley describes the emotions Gloria went through after she received the news and how she was coping with the death of her fiancé. She also tells how Gloria received back over a hundred letters she sent her fiancé that he had never received and describes the level of Gloria’s distress at this information.
  Shirley's own frustration with the mail is another frequent theme of her letters. There were chronic mail delays, both from the US to soldiers and from soldiers to the US, and Shirley could go weeks without hearing from Lester. The letters also provide insight into the difficulty of communicating in the pre-digital world. For example, Shirley describes organizing a trip to San Francisco to see Lester after receiving a letter from him in Manila telling her to meet him in San Francisco on August 5, 1945. She explains how she communicated with various people and hotels to organize the trip through letters and telegrams and outlines the difficulties in organizing this trip due to being unsure as to when he was actually arriving in San Francisco.
  Shirley’s letters provide an interesting insight into how the people of New York reacted to details that were emerging about the war. In a letter dated April 14, 1945, she describes a tribute paid to Roosevelt before a show she attended at Radio City and tells how sobbing could be heard throughout the audience. In a letter dated May 1, 1945 she describes the emotions she felt about hearing of the death of Hitler and tells how the news showed ‘atrocity pictures of the German concentration camps’. In a letter dated May 7th she discusses the unconditional surrender of the Germans and describes the reactions of people she knows who have lost loved ones. She describes the general feeling in New York concerning the victory in Europe and explains how it is quieter than expected as many of the New York troops were still stationed in the South Pacific, and for those men and their families, the war was not yet over.
  - Letters, August 1942, 1942 August 28 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Letters, September & October 1943, 1943 September 7- October 26 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Letters; October, November, December 1944, & January 1945, 1944 October 13 -1945 January 18 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Includes newspaper clippings that Shirley included in her letters to Lester.
  - Letters, February & March 1945, 1945 February 1 - March 26 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Letters, April 1945, 1945 April 6-30 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters, May & June 1945, 1945 May 1 - June 25 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Letters, July & August 1945, 1945 July 1 - August 29th (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Letters, October 1945, 1945 October 4-31 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Letters, November 1945, 1945 November 1-8 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Series III: Letters and cards from family and friends to both Shirley and Lester
  Includes letters, cards, and postcards to Lester from his friends and family. Also includes documents relating to the Halbreich's wedding and the birth of their son, a collection of birthday cards for Jeffrey Halbreich's 1st and 2nd birthdays, and letters to Shirley from Abe Greenstein and others.
  - Cards, postcards, and letters to Lester from Shirley and others, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Lester from his family and friends, Bulk, 1943-1945; 1941-1946 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Includes a V Mail letter from Lester's aunt and a letter from Ralph (his closest friend on the Oxford) dated 1946.
  - Letters to Shirley from Abe Greenstein and others, 1941-1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Documents relating to the Halbreich's wedding and the birth of their son, 1941, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Birthday cards for Jeffrey Halbreich's 1st and 2nd birthdays, 1944 July 28 & 1945 July 28 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Related documents, Circa 1941-1945 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Includes a V Mail letter from a family member to Shirley's mother.